Guide to the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom Collection ARS.0056
Archive of Recorded Sound
- 5. Branches Outside California., 1986-1989
  - 22. Louise Robison Interview., 1988-11-09 and 1988-12-14; Pederson, Sharon; Robison, Louise
    - Interview, December 14, 1988., 1988-12-14; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 203)
    - Bio/historical note; Index., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - 23. Siphra Rolland Interview., 1987-12-30; Gamble, Dee; Rolland, Siphra
    - Interview, December 30, 1987., 1987-12-30; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 204)
    - Bio/historical note., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - 24. Phyllis Sanders Interview., 1987-10-06; Adams, Judith Porter; Sanders, Phyllis
    - Interview, October 6, 1987, Part One., 1987-10-06; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 205)
    - Interview, October 6, 1987, Part Two., 1987-10-06; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 206)
    - Bio/historical note., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - 25. Eldora Spiegelberg Interview., 1988-10-05 to 1988-10-12; Pederson, Sharon; Spiegelberg, Eldora
    - Interview, October 5, 1988., 1988-10-05; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 207)
    - Interview, October 12, 1988., 1988-10-12; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 208)
    - Bio/historical note; Index; Newspaper clipping, March 30, 1988., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - 26. Amy Swerdlow Interview., 1987-09-25; Adams, Judith Porter; Swerdlow, Amy
    - Interview, September 25, 1987, Part One., 1987-09-25; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 209)
    - Interview, September 25, 1987, Part Two., 1987-09-25; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 210)
    - Bio/historical note; Index; Transcript; Obituary; Article citations., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - 27. Catharine Taylor Interview., 1988-01-25; Paisley, John; Paisley, Miriam; Taylor, Catharine
    - Bio/historical note; Transcript., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - 28. Ethel Barol Taylor Interview., 1987-10-05; Adams, Judith Porter; Taylor, Ethel Barol
    - Interview, October 5, 1987, Part One., 1987-10-05; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 211)
    - Interview, October 5, 1987, Part Two., 1987-10-05; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 212)
    - Program for the 25th Birthday Party for Women Strike for Peace, November 22, 1986; Program for the 23rd Anniversary Celebration for Women Strike for Peace Honoring Ethel Taylor, November 17, 1984; Photo of Statue by Ethel Taylor, May 15, 1982; Newspaper article, December 10-17, 1998; Newpaper article, March 28, 1977; Other papers; Transcript; Obituary; Image of Baby in the Air sculpture., 1 folder (Audio 12, Folder 17)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - 29. Edith Villastrigo Interview., 1987-10; Adams, Judith Porter; Villastrigo, Edith
    - Interview, October 1987, Part One., 1987-10; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 213)
    - Interview, October 1987, Part Two., 1987-10; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 214)
    - Newspaper article, August 29, 2001; Newspaper clipping, August 21, 1987;., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - 30. Lillian Willoughby Interview., 1987-09-28; Adams, Judith Porter; Willoughby, Lillian, 1915 -
    - Interview, September 28, 1987., 1987-09-28; 1 audiocassette (Audio 6, Cassette 215)
    - Bio/historical note; Index; Newspaper clipping, Summer 1987; Newpaper clipping, April 14, 1982; Newspaper clipping, January 23, 1974; Newspaper clipping, May 9, 1982; Other papers., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - 31. Cora Weiss interview., 1987-09-24; Adams, Judith Porter; Weiss, Cora, 1934-
    - Interview, September 24, 1987, Part One., 1987-09-24; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 233)
    - Interview, September 24, 1987, Part Two., 1987-09-24; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 234)
    - Transcript; Articles; Presentations; Other papers., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 56)
  - 32. Dagmar Wilson Interview., 1989-04-15; Drake, Joan; Wilson, Dagmar
    - Interview, April 15, 1989, Part One., 1989-04-15; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 216)
    - Interview, April 15, 1989, Part Two., 1989-04-15; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 217)
    - Bio/historical note; Obituary; Article citations., 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Photographs., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 57)
- 6. Class Presentations., 1967 to 1984; 15 audiocassettes
  - Joan Baez and Ira Sandperl Presentation at the 1967 Asilomar Conference., 1967-06-23; 1 audiocassette; Baez, Joan; Sandperl, Ira (Audio 7, Cassette 218)
    Location of Original
    This is a copy of Box 9, Reel 266.
  - Nan Bixler Presentation on Nuclear Freeze., 1984-03-20; 1 audiocassette; Bixler, Nanon (Nan) (Audio 7, Cassette 219)
  - Kay Camp Speech at NE Regional WILPF Conference., 1980; 1 audiocassette; Camp, Kay (Audio 7, Cassette 220)
  - Alice Cox Presentation at San Jose Peace Center., 1984; 1 audiocassette; Cox, Alice (Audio 7, Cassette 221)
  - Peg Ellwell Presentation on Jobs with Peace., 1984-03-29; 1 audiocassette; Ellwell, Peg (Audio 7, Cassette 222)
  - Greenham Common Women., 1984-01-31; 1 audiocassette 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 223)
  - Lois Helmhold Presentation., 1984-01-14; 1 audiocassette; Helmhold, Lois (Audio 7, Cassette 224)
  - Helen Mehr Presentation on Physicians for Social Responsibility., 1984-04-05; 1 audiocassette; Mehr, Helen (Audio 7, Cassette 225)
  - Esther Newill Presentation on Santa Rita Prison, Livermore Protests., 1983-08; 1 audiocassette; Newill, Esther (Audio 7, Cassette 226)
  - Alice Richards Presentation on Women's Strike for Peace and Ellen Schwartz Presentation at San Jose WILPF., 1984-03-01; 1 audiocassette; Richards, Alice (Audio 7, Cassette 227)
  - Linda Schott Presentation on the Women's Peace Party and WILPF., 1984-02-09; 1 audiocassette; Schott, Linda (Audio 7, Cassette 228)
  - Natalie Shiras Presentation on Living in the Nuclear Age., 1984-03-22; 1 audiocassette; Shiras, Natalie (Audio 7, Cassette 229)
  - Barbara Ulmer Presentation on AFSC and Our Developing World., 1984-02-02; 1 audiocassette; Ulmer, Barbara (Audio 7, Cassette 230)
  - Barbara Ulmer Presentation on Women and South Africa., 1984; 1 audiocassette; Ulmer, Barbara (Audio 7, Cassette 231)
  - WILPF Project Slideshow Script., 1983-06-01; 2 item(s) 1 audiocassette; Loose leaves (Audio 7, Cassette 232, Box 13, Folder 11)
- 7. WILPF 1967 National Conference at Asilomar, CA., 13 7" open reel tape(s)
  - Betty Polster presiding. Eleanor Norton (worked with Joseph Rank in civil rights, Antioch). Anne Ginger Wood (law)., 1967-06-11; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 258)
  - Marsha Windmiller, “Peace and Politics”., 1967-06-19; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 259)
  - Windmiller contd. Answers to questions (Dr. Bayer: International pressure, anticommunist forces on the left.)., 1967-06-19; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 260)
  - Ruth Gage Colby; Panel: Elise Boulding. Windmiller – freedom to dissent in US, hippies’ alienation, important to make concessions in order to have influence., 1967-06-19; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 261)
  - Opening session: Selma Le Shack on the UN. Lois Hamer – background of S. E. Asia., 1967-06-20; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 262)
  - contd. Hamer Q&A., 1967-06-20; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 263)
  - Evening session - Elizabeth Polster: People, Power and Peace., 1967-06-20; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 264)
  - Afternoon: Anne Ginger Wood and Panel (Wood, Reichert – Fair Housing)., 1967-06-20; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 265)
  - Evening with Joan Baez and Ira Sandperl on Non-Violence. Questions (song by Joan near end)., 1967-06-22; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 266)
    Location of Copy
    A audiocassette copy of this reel can be found in Box 7, Cassette 218.
  - [empty box]., 1967-06-23; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 267)
  - Asilomar -conclusion., 1967-06-23; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 268)
  - Jo Graham, Donna Adler., undated; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 269)
  - Joan Baez and Ira Sandperl., 1967-06-23; 1 7" open reel tape(s) (Audio 9, Reel 270)
- 8. Supplemental Materials., circa 1915-2011; 1 box
  - 1. Project Publicity., circa 1984-2010; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Program, From Hull House to Human Rights: A Jane Addams Symposium, September 24, 2010., 2010-09-24
    - Palo Alto Weekly News article on WILPF, June 13, 1984., 1984-06-13
    - Newspaper article, April 15, 1985: Women Working for peace, 60 years ago., 1985-04-15
    - Program, Live Feminist Theater.
    - Publishing promotion: Piecework: Oral Histories of Women Working for Peace.
    - Publishing promotion: Peacework: Oral Histories of Women Peace Activists, by Judith Porter Adams.
    - Newspaper article by Becky Fischbach, Stanford Daily.
    - Newspaper clipping, March 19, 1986., 1986-03-19
    - Newspaper clipping, March 1984., 1984-03
    - “Grandmother’s march” in Palo Alto, CA. Used as image for project’s letterhead., 2 photograph(s)
    - Handout: WILPF Oral History Project Presentation., 1983-04-22; 2 leaves (typescript)
  - 2. Project Materials., undated; 3 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 2, Folder 12, Folder 13)
    - Letter requesting participation in Women's Peace Oral History Project.
    - Palo Alto/Stanford University WILPF Oral History Project Report, by Judy Adams, Linda Shaw, and Becky Fischbach.
    - Women's Peace Oral History Interview Guidelines.
    - Photo releases.
    - Interview releases.
  - 3. Palo Alto WILPF History., circa 1922-1994; 4 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 3, Folder 8, Folder 9, Folder 10)
    - Palo Alto Centennial article, April 13, 1994: The tumultuous '60s., 1994-04-13
    - WILPF Palo Alto Branch Chronology 1960-1980.
    - Meeting minutes: 1922, 1926, and 1939-1947., 1922-1947; 3 scrapbooks
  - 4. International WILPF History., circa 1915-1975; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - The WILPF Story... then and now.
    - WILPF Chronology 1915-1963.
    - Time Line for WPO History Project 1961-1975.
    - WILPF Chronology 1933-1962.
  - 5. Student Papers., 1981-1984; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Voices from Outside: Women's Connections to Peace and Nonviolence, by Margaret Jacobs, March 6, 1984., 1984-03-06
    - The Hazards of Nuclear Waste, by Peggy Nutz, May 1984., 1984-05
    - Research Paper: The Progressive Party, by Mary Jeffries, May 29, 1984., 1984-05-29
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom: World War II and its Implications for Pacifism, by Amy Levenson, February 25, 1981., 1981-02-25
  - 6. Other Papers., circa 2011; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Role of San Francisco Women for Peace in the U.S. War Against Vietnam, unknown author.
    - WILPF Resources at Stanford.
    - Y-WILPF: taking steps to leadership roles.
    - Women Strike for Peace: 50 years later. Blog post by Chanel Dubofsky., 2011-11-02
    - How did women in civil society challenge McCarthyism in ways that men could not? Women Strike for Peace in 1961-62. Online article by Harvey Binghamton.
    - Piecework: Life Stories of Women Working for Peace. Original book design by Becky Fischbach.
  - 7. Other Audio., 1983-1985; 2 audiocassettes
    - Mothertongue Feminist Theater Collective at the Palo Alto Varsity Theatre., 1985-04-28; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 235)
      Audio of a live performance by Mothertongue Feminist Theater Collective of a script they composed, based on interview transcripts and excerpts from the WILPF project. The performance was accompanied by projected images of the women interviewed.
    - WILPF Slide Show., 1983-04; 1 audiocassette (Audio 7, Cassette 236)
  - 8. Other Photographs., undated; 2 folders
    - Peg Dunham, Palo Alto Chapter., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Palo Alto Peace Center., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - San Jose Peace Class., 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - Syllabus: Oral Histories of Political Women., 1981; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 6)
- 9. Monographs., 1963-2001; 9 books
  - Adams, Judith Porter. (1991). Peacework: Oral Histories of Women Peace Activists. Boston: Twayne Publishers., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Greene, Felix. (1963). Let There be a World. Palo Alto, CA: The Fulton Publishing Company., 1 book (Box 13)
    Hildreth, Helen
  - Hamburg, Alice Sachs. (2001). Grass Roots: From Prairie to Politics. Berkeley, CA: Creative Arts Book Company., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Lucey, Rose Marciano. (1987). Roots and Wings. San Jose, CA: Resource Publications, Inc., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Pershing, Linda. (1996). The Ribbon around the Pentagon: Peace by Piecemakers. Knoxville, TN: The University of Tennessee Press., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Schott, Linda K. (1997). Reconstructing Women’s Thoughts: The Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom Before World War I., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Swerdlow, Amy. (1993). Women Strike For Peace: Traditional Motherhood and Radical Politics in the 1960s., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Taylor, Ethel Barol. (1998). We Made a Difference: My Personal Journey with Women Strike for Peace. Philadelphia: Camino Books, Inc., 1 book (Box 13)
  - Von der Muhll, Anthony. (1987). Fighting Her Way: An Oral History of Lucy Haessler. A thesis submitted for the degree of Bachelor of Arts (HIstory) at the University of California at Santa Cruz., 1 book (Box 13)
    Scope and Conents
    Includes transcripts of the interviews conducted with Haessler as part of the Women's Peace Oral History project.
- 10. Photographic negatives and 35mm slides., 1967-1989; 1 box 3 boxes of slides and 1 envelope of unsorted negatives (Box 14)
  Inventory
  A printed inventory of the 35mm slides in also in Box 14.